<chapter title="FAQ - Frequently Asked Questions">

<section title="What is this all about ?">

<p>Ok, AROS is a rewrite of AmigaOS 3.1 (Kickstart 40.68 and up).</p>

<p>These are the main goals:</p>

<ol>
<li>Be binary compatible on Amiga (so it can plug&amp;play replace the
original OS)</li>

<li>Be source compatible on any other hardware (so Amiga software can be
ported to other hardwares with no effort)</li>

<li>Provide every hardware with Amiga apps with native look and feel or,
as the user chooses, foreign hardware with Amiga look and feel.</li>

<li>AROS will come in three flavours: 1) A standalone OS like Linux, Win,
etc. 2) An Amiga Emulation (ie. a window in which you have a Workbench.
Every new screen will open a new window) 3) A link-library with which you
can port Amiga apps to other OSs (eg. Windows). 1) will have Amiga look&amp;feel,
2) will have a mixture and 3) will have native look&amp;feel.
The flavours 1 and 2 will optionally have binary compatibility if
possible.</li>

</ol>

</section>
<section title="Why do you implement the current OS ?">

<p>There have been some talks about writing something which is something like
an advanced OS with the features of the AmigaOS. This has been dropped
for a good reason. First, everyone agrees that the current AmigaOS
should be enhanced, but no one knows how to do that or even agrees on what
has to be enhanced or what is important. Some want memory protection, but
don't want to pay the price (major rewrite of the available software and
speed cut-offs).</p>

<p>In the end, the discussions ended in either flame wars or "do it this
way ! - Won't work because !". So we just said: First we do something we
know to handle. Then we have the experience to decide what is possible
and how. And then we decide.</p>

<p>Also we want to be binary compatible to the old AmigaOS on Amiga. The
reason for this is just that a new OS without any programs which run on
it has no chance to survive. Therefore we try to make the shift from
the old OS to our new one as painless as possible (but not to the
extent that we can't improve AROS afterwards). As usual, everything
has its price and we try to decide carefully what that price might be
and if we and everyone else will be willing to pay it.</p>

</section>
<section title="Please implement this feature !">

<p>No. a) If it was that important, it would be in the OS already :-) b) Why
don't you do it yourself and send it to us ?</p>

<p>See, there are plenty of people around who think that their feature is the
most important and that "the AmigaOS has no future if this feature is not
built in right now". We say: The AmigaOS' demise has nothing to do with
missing features. The AmigaOS can do everything a modern OS should do. We
see that there are possibilities to enhance the AmigaOS, but if we do it,
who would write the rest of the OS ? In the end, we would have lots of
nice improvements to the original AmigaOS which would break most of the
available software and worth nothing, because the OS itself would be
missing. So we decided to block every attempt to implement major new
features in the OS until it's more or less done.</p>

</section>
<section title="What is the legal status of AROS ?">

<p>AROS is Open Source as defined by the APL which is derived from the
Mozilla Public License (we replaced the name "Mozilla" by "AROS" and
modified some text so that all files below the AROS source directory
are subject to the license). <a href="license.html">Here is an online
version</a>.
</p>

<p>If you want to use AROS' code in your own project, you may do so
without paying us a fee but if you modify the source, you must
at least open the interface to the new functionality so that we
can provide a compatible replacement for other users. We also would
like you to state explicitly that you are using our work so that
we can be proud :-)
</p>

</section>
<section title="How legal is AROS ?">

<p>Well, European law says "To gain interoperability, it is legal to apply
reverse engineering techniques. It is illegal to distribute the knowledge
gained by such techiques". So what does that mean ? It means basically that
you are allowed to disassemble or resource any software to write something
which is compatible (ie. it would be legal to disassemble Word to write a
program which converts Word into ASCII text).</p>

<p>Now there are of course limitations: You are not allowed to disassemble a
software if the information you would gain by this process can be obtained
by other means and it can be expected that one would use this is other
means. And you must not tell others what you learned. A book like
"Windows inside" is therefore illegal or at least dubious.</p>

<p>Since we avoid disassembling techniques (hey, we want the spirit and not
the bugs) but use common available knowledge (including programming
manuals) which don't fall below the NDA, this doesn't apply directly to
AROS, but what counts here is the intention of the law: It's ok to write a
software which is compatible to some other software. Therefore we believe
that AROS is protected by the law.</p>

<p>Patents and header files are a different issue, though. We can use patented
algorithms (eg. screen dragging or getting a menu when you press the
right mousebutton) in Europe but this must not be imported into the US.
Header files on the other hand must be compatible but "as different as
possible" from the orignal.</p>

<p>Therefore to avoid any trouble we applied for an official Ok by Amiga Inc.
Amiga Inc is quite positive about the effort but they are very uneasy
about the legal implications. We suggest that you take that fact that
Amiga Inc did not send us any Cease&amp;Desist letters (yet) as a
positive sign. Unfortunately, no legal sound agreement could be made
yet besides good intentions on both sides.</p>

</section>
<section title="How compatible is AROS ?">

<p>Most compatible. We expect that AROS will run existing software on the
Amiga without problems. On other hardware (like PCs), the existing
software must be recompiled. We will offer a preprocessor which you can
use on your code which will change any code that might break with AROS
and/or warn you about such code.</p>

</section>
<section title="For what kinds of hardware is AROS available ?">

<p>Currently AROS is available for Intel PCs with Linux (Linux/i386) or
FreeBSD and Amiga with AmigaOS and Linux/m68. We are working on versions
for SPARC, HPUX, Alpha, PIOS ONE/transAm and any other available
hardware if someone wants to do that.</p>

<ol>
<li>Linux/i386 with 2.x kernel. Status: everything works. Flavours: Emulation</li>
<li>IBM PC Status: Some parts work. Flavours: Native</li>
<li>FreeBSD/i386: Status: everything works. Flavours: Emulation</li>
<li>Amiga/AmigaOS: Status: parts work (like a big SetPatch()). Flavours: Standalone</li>
<li>Linux/m68k: Status: alpha. Flavours: Emulation (binary compatible)</li>
</ol>

<p>There have been efforts to port AROS to PPC and Sparc (Sun) but
these projects did not take off. If you want AROS on PPC, you should
wait for MorphOS because the people behind MorphOS are using AROS to
fill in the missing parts in their Amiga emulator.</p>

</section>
<section title="How about UAE ?">

<p>UAE is an A500 emulator. Its goals differ somewhat from that of AROS: UAE
wants to be able to be binary compatible even for games and hardware
banging code, while AROS wants to have native applications. Therefore AROS
is much faster than UAE, but UAE has more software.</p>

<p>We are in loose contact with the author of UAE and there is a good chance
that code for UAE will appear in AROS and vice versa. For example, UAE is
interested in the source for the OS because it could run some apps much
faster if it could replace the OS calls by native code. On the other hand,
AROS needs hardware drivers (eg. audio.device).</p>

<p>Since most code will not be available on AROS from the start, 
Fabio Alemagna has started to port UAE to AROS so you can at least
run the old code in an emulation box. Since we concentrated on
writing AmigaOS functions, many functions of the c.lib are still
missing, so this will take some time.</p>

</section>
<section title="You should not use Linux or X11 !">

<p>The final version of AROS will not depend on Linux or X11 anymore (but
it will run on them if you insist). Currently, we use Linux and X11 to
speed up development. For example, if I write a new function to open
a window, I can write that single function and need not write hundreds
of other functions in layers, graphics, etc.</p>

</section>
<section title="How do you want to make it portable ?">

<p>One of the major new features of AROS will be the new Hardware
Independent Device Drivers (HIDD). They will allow us to port AROS to
any hardware with almost no fuzz. But that's a bit in the future. So
don't worry that your old code won't work anymore, say, next month.</p>

</section>
<section title="AROS won't make it">

<p>Yeah, we hear that all the day from every person. But most of them
either don't know what we are doing or they think the Amiga is already dead.
After we explained what we do to the former, most agreed that it
is possible. The latter make more problems. Well, is Amiga dead right
now ? I really can't say. Just a few hints: Did your A500 or A4000 blew up
when C= went bankrupt ? Or when AT did ?</p>

<p>Fact is that there is only few new software for the Amiga (although Aminet
has never seen better times) and that hardware is also developed at
a lower speed (but the most amazing gadgets appear right now). I say,
the Amiga community (which is still there) just sits and waits. And if
someone releases something which is a bit like the Amiga back in 1984,
then that machine will boom again. And who knows, maybe you will get
a CD along with the machine labeled "AROS" :-)</p>

</section>
<section title="AROS won't compile">

<p>Please post a message with details (for example, the error messages
you get) on the <a href="/mailman/listinfo/aros-user/">AROS-User</a>
mailing list or become a developer and subscribe to the
<a href="/mailman/listinfo/aros-dev/">AROS-Dev</a> list.
</p>

</section>
<section title="What do I need to compile AROS ?">

<p>You need either a Linux distribution
(<a href="http://www.suse.com">SuSE</a> usually works,
<a href="http://www.redhat.com">RedHat</a> usually less :-)</p>

</section>
<section title="Memory protection, VMM, RT, ...">

<p>Hot themes. Oh well...</p>

<p>Several hundred Amiga experts (or at least what they thought of themselves)
tried for three years to find a way to implement MP (memory protection)
into the AmigaOS. They failed. You should take it as a fact that the
normal AmigaOS will never have something like Unix or WindowsNT.</p>

<p>But not all is lost. There are plans to integrate MP into AROS which will
allow to protect at least new programs which know about MP. Some efforts
in this area look really promising and in the end: Is it really a problem
if your machine crashes ? Let me explain, before you nail me to a tree :-)
The problem is not that the machine crashes, the problems are: 1. If
that happens, you have no good idea why it did, so you have to poke
with a 100ft pole into a swamp with a thick fog. 2. You loose your work.
Rebooting the machine is really no issue.</p>

<p>So what we try to establish is a system which will at least alert if
something dubious is happening and which can tell you in great detail what
was happening when the machine crashed and which will save your work and
*then* crash. There will also be a means to check what has been saved so you
can be sure that you don't continue with corrupted data.</p>

<p>The same with VMM, RT, SMP and RTG. We are currently planning how to
implement them and we make sure that adding these features will be painless,
but they are no #1 priorities right now. A very basic RT has been added,
though.</p>

</section>
<section title="How about PPC or PPC cards ?">

<p>We are regularily asked about AROS on PPC. The answer has always been the
same: While many people ask, no one applies to do the work. Currently,
the best bet for AROS on PPC is probably MorphOS.</p>

</section>
<section title="I want to be a beta tester">

<p>Sure, no problem. But we don't keep a list of beta testers, so all you have
to do is to download the part of AROS you want to test and send us the
report.</p>

</section>
<section title="What mailing lists are there ?">

<p>See the <a href="links.html">Links section</a>.</p>

</section>
<section title="AROS and MorphOS">

<p>MorphOS is a new PPC based computer system. It runs Linux and an
AmigaOS emulator which can run programs compiled for the Amiga.
The people behind MorphOS are very interested in AROS and have
begun to port parts of AROS' code to their system to fill the
gaps.</p>

<p>There have been rumours that AROS and MorphOS have joined
forces. This is not so. The AROS team is still independent.
MorphOS is just using a part of our work. Isn't this what
Open Source is all about ?
</p>

</section>
<section title="AROS and H&amp;P">

<p><a href="www.haage-partner.de">Haage&amp;Partner</a> have used
a part of AROS, namely the Colorwheel gadget in OS 3.9. So in a way,
AROS has become part of the official AmigaOS. Of course, this
doesn't imply anything. AROS has not become the development branch
of Amiga Inc :-)</p>

</section>
<section title="What programming languages are available ?">

<p>Currently, all development is done in ANSI C. We just use some tools
to automatically generate the C header files (clib, protos, pragmas, fds)
and AutoDocs from the sources and <a href="mmake.html">MetaMake</a>
to build everything.</p>

<p>There are some plans to port at least a C compiler to AROS, so we
could compile code inside of AROS instead of cross compiling but that
will take some time. For example, we need some extensions to C (namely the
Macro Varargs of GCC) to make TagLists work. Then some people are
investigating to port a BASIC dialect to AROS and Aaron Digulla
wants Python. These are still future plans, though.</p>

</section>
</chapter>
